<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: storm | nerding.out()]]></title>
  <link href="http://kakar.ca/blog/categories/storm/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kakar.ca/"/>
  <updated>2013-01-30T17:56:19-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://kakar.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jamu Kakar]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Storm 0.17 is out in the world!]]></title>
    <link href="http://kakar.ca/blog/2010/08/06/storm-0-dot-17-is-out-in-the-world/"/>
    <updated>2010-08-06T12:25:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://kakar.ca/blog/2010/08/06/storm-0-dot-17-is-out-in-the-world</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday I released version 0.17 of
<a href="http://storm.canonical.com/">Storm</a>.  This release fixes a
checkpointing bug that could cause coherency issues in certain
situations involving triggers.  It introduces a handful of new
features and optimizations including the ability to get a
<a href="http://people.canonical.com/~therve/storm/storm.expr.Select.html"><code>Select</code></a>
expression from a
<a href="http://people.canonical.com/~jkakar/storm/storm.store.ResultSet.html"><code>ResultSet</code></a>,
which is useful when building a query with a subselect.  It also
includes safety checks to ensure that a
<a href="http://people.canonical.com/~therve/storm/storm.store.Store.html"><code>Store</code></a>
is only used when database access is expected and only from the thread
in which it was created.  The
<a href="http://launchpad.net/storm/+milestone/0.17">release notes</a> have
detailed information about the changes along with links to the MD5 sum
and GPG signature for the
<a href="http://edge.launchpad.net/storm/trunk/0.17/+download/storm-0.17.tar.bz2">tarball</a>.
I've also built official packages for Ubuntu users, available in the
<a href="https://launchpad.net/~storm/+archive/ppa">Storm PPA</a>.</p>

<p>We're always interested in hearing about your experiences with Storm.
If you have comments or questions please feel free to hop into
<code>#storm</code> on Freenode and talk to us, or post a message on the
<a href="https://lists.canonical.com/mailman/listinfo/storm">mailing list</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Object collections in Storm]]></title>
    <link href="http://kakar.ca/blog/2010/06/13/object-collections-in-storm/"/>
    <updated>2010-06-13T12:25:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://kakar.ca/blog/2010/06/13/object-collections-in-storm</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In <a href="https://storm.canonical.com/">Storm</a>, the
<a href="http://people.canonical.com/~therve/storm/storm.store.Store.html#find"><code>Store.find</code></a>
method runs a query and returns matching objects.  Finding all
accounts in the database, the equivalent of <code>SELECT * FROM account</code>,
is simple:</p>

<p><code>python
result = store.find(Account)
</code></p>

<p>Clauses to limit the scope of the query can be passed to find.
Finding all accounts owned by Vince Offer, the equivalent of <code>SELECT *
FROM account WHERE owner = ‘Vince Offer'</code>, is also simple:</p>

<p><code>python
result = store.find(Account, Account.owner == "Vince Offer")
</code></p>

<p>Another way to achieve the same thing is to take the result from the
first find operation and refine it:</p>

<p><code>python
result1 = store.find(Account)
result2 = result1.find(Account.owner == "Vince Offer")
</code></p>

<p>Storm doesn't run a query until you do something with the result, so
the impact on the database is exactly the same as in the previous
example.  This is the simplest form of what
<a href="http://code.mumak.net/">Jonathan</a> and I have been calling the
collection pattern.  The basic idea is that you start with a
collection of all objects, and then refine it, until you have the
collection you want.  This pattern is possible using pure Storm, as
shown above, but we've found it useful to implement objects that hide
this logic and provide a more user friendly API.  For example, an
<code>AccountCollection</code> would provide filtering logic as named methods:</p>

<p>``` python
class AccountCollection(object):</p>

<pre><code>def owned_by(self, salesman):
    """
    Get a new collection with accounts owned by
    salesman.
    """

def has_unpaid_invoices(self):
    """
    Get a new collection with accounts that have
    unpaid invoices.
    """

def find(self):
    """Get a result set of matching accounts."""
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Each filtering method, such as <code>owned_by</code> and <code>has_unpaid_invoices</code>
returns a new <code>AccountCollection</code> instance.  This isn't strictly
necessary but creating a new instance is both easier to understand and
implement.  Finding all accounts owned by <code>Vince Offer</code> that have unpaid
invoices is quite easy:</p>

<p><code>python
collection1 = AccountCollection()
collection2 = collection1.owned_by("Vince Offer")
collection3 = collection2.has_unpaid_invoices()
result = collection3.find()
</code></p>

<p>This pattern provides several benefits:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>It names filtering options which makes them easy to understand and
use.</p></li>
<li><p>Query building logic is in one place which eliminates duplication.</p></li>
<li><p>All the criteria used to build a query are available when the query
is generated, which makes it possible to generate optimized queries.
All users of the collection benefit from optimizations.</p></li>
<li><p>It creates a clean separation between finding data and using it.
This helps keep application logic more focused, because it isn't
intermingled with the particulars of generating queries.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>We've used this pattern to good effect in both
<a href="https://landscape.canonical.com/">Landscape</a> and
<a href="https://launchpad.net/">Launchpad</a>.  In a future post I'll talk about
some different strategies we've used to implement the pattern.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using SQL functions with Storm]]></title>
    <link href="http://kakar.ca/blog/2010/04/08/using-sql-functions-with-storm/"/>
    <updated>2010-04-08T12:25:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://kakar.ca/blog/2010/04/08/using-sql-functions-with-storm</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>People ask me questions about <a href="https://storm.canonical.com/">Storm</a>
several times a week, and I'm happy to help where I can, but it would
be better if the information our users need was easier to find.  Our
documentation story is weak and, as a result, Storm is harder to
discover than it ought to be.  If you do run into problems or have
questions, please hop into <code>#storm</code> on Freenode and we'll do our best
to help you.  I want to improve the documentation situation, but
finding the time to do so hasn't happened yet.  The next best thing is
to post some helpful hints here.</p>

<p>First, some advice: if you don't know what SQL query you want to run,
using Storm will probably be hard.  When I get asked a question about
writing a query using Storm I almost always respond with, "What does
the query you want to run look like?" The querying part of Storm is
essentially just an expression compiler that takes a list of
expressions and converts them to SQL.  Once you know what end result
you want, working backwards to figure out the Storm parlance is
relatively straight forward.</p>

<p>Today I was asked about using
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Null_%28SQL%29#COALESCE"><code>COALESCE</code></a>.
The person asking the question found the
<a href="http://people.canonical.com/~therve/storm/storm.expr.Coalesce.html"><code>storm.expr.Coalesce</code></a>
expression but it wasn't obvious how to use it.  He knew he wanted to
run a query like:</p>

<p><code>sql
SELECT * FROM table WHERE COALESCE(col1, col2) = 'foo'
</code></p>

<p>With that knowledge, figuring out how to use Storm was quite easy:</p>

<p><code>sql
store.find(Table, Coalesce(Table.col1, Table.col2) == "foo")
</code></p>

<p>Furthermore, <code>Coalesce</code> is just a helper expression to aid usability
and readability.  If we didn't have a built-in <code>Coalesce</code> expression
the query could have been written using the generic
<a href="http://people.canonical.com/~therve/storm/storm.expr.Func.html"><code>storm.expr.Func</code></a>
expression:</p>

<p><code>sql
store.find(Table, Func("COALESCE", Table.col1, Table.col2) == "foo")
</code></p>

<p>If you want to use a SQL function in a Storm query, and there is no
built-in expression for it, you can use <code>Func</code> to call it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Talking about Storm]]></title>
    <link href="http://kakar.ca/blog/2009/12/02/talking-about-storm/"/>
    <updated>2009-12-02T12:14:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://kakar.ca/blog/2009/12/02/talking-about-storm</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I gave a talk about <a href="http://storm.canonical.com/">Storm</a> to the
fine folks that make up the local
<a href="http://wiki.python.org/moin/VanPyZ">Python users group</a>. I think the
talk went alright.  It wasn't awesome but I don't think it was
terrible either.  It's the third public talk I've given, pretty much
ever, and so I have a lot to learn about the process.  The group is
friendly and I felt comfortable standing up in front of everyone and
yammering on about Storm.</p>

<p>In retrospect, I should have come up with much better example code.  I
didn't make enough time to prepare and, due to rushing at the end, the
topics I covered were rather basic.  I did an experiment and wrote a
psuedo-doctest to use as slides.  The doctest and a script to run it
are available at
<a href="https://code.launchpad.net/~jkakar/+junk/storm-talk">lp:~jkakar/+junk/storm-talk</a>.
I used a slightly hacked version of
<a href="https://launchpad.net/~mwhudson">Michael Hudson-Doyle's</a> very awesome
<a href="http://launchpad.net/console-presenter">console-presenter</a>, which is
available at
<a href="https://code.launchpad.net/~jkakar/console-presenter/two-line-separator">lp:~jkakar/console-presenter/two-line-separator</a>.</p>

<p>The format was great for getting me to focus on content, even though I
didn't have enough time to do a great job preparing it, but the slides
were a bit lackluster being grey text on a black background.  Also, a
common problem with doctests is that you need to keep track of the
state of the program as you read the document.  I think this problem
made the format awkward for the audience.  It was a good experiment,
but in the future I'll use traditional slides, and try to avoid a
situation that requires the audience to keep program state in their
head as the talk progresses.  Funny how these things seem so obvious
in hindsight.</p>

<p><a href="http://douglatornell.ca/">Doug Latornell</a> gave a nice talk about his
experiences using <a href="http://pyyaml.org/">PyYAML</a>,
<a href="http://stuvel.eu/projects/flickrapi">flickerapi</a> and
<a href="http://wiki.python.org/moin/TkInter">Tkinter</a> to build an application
that displays random photos on his living room TV, both from his
personal collection and from his favourite groups on Flickr.  I
enjoyed the talk and the discussion it spurred.</p>

<p>All in all it was a good experience and from which I've learnt some
lessons, which I can hopefully use to make the next talk better.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Storm 0.16 hot off the presses!]]></title>
    <link href="http://kakar.ca/blog/2009/11/29/storm-0-dot-16-hot-off-the-presses/"/>
    <updated>2009-11-29T12:01:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://kakar.ca/blog/2009/11/29/storm-0-dot-16-hot-off-the-presses</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday I released version 0.16 of
<a href="http://storm.canonical.com/">Storm</a>.  This release fixes some memory
leaks and introduces a handful of new features.  The number of changes
since 0.15 aren't vast, but we're trying to get into the habit of
releasing regularly, so hopefully this will become a trend. The
<a href="http://launchpad.net/storm/+milestone/0.16">release notes</a> have
detailed information about the changes along with links to the MD5 sum
and GPG signature for the
<a href="http://launchpad.net/storm/trunk/0.16/+download/storm-0.16.0.tar.bz2">tarball</a>.
I've also built official packages for Ubuntu users, available in the
<a href="https://launchpad.net/~storm/+archive/ppa">Storm PPA</a>.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, the <code>karmic</code> and <code>lucid</code> packages don't work properly
because they install files in <code>/usr/lib/python2.6/site-packages</code>,
which is no longer included in <code>sys.path</code> by default.  In the next
couple of days I'll build new packages that correctly install files in
<code>/usr/lib/python2.6/dist-packages</code>, which should fix the problem.  For
now, adding the <code>site-packages</code> path to <code>sys.path</code> or including it in
<code>PYTHONPATH</code> will workaround the issue.</p>

<p>We're always interested in hearing about your experiences with Storm.
If you have comments or questions please feel free to hop into
<code>#storm</code> on Freenode and chat us up, or post a message to the
<a href="https://lists.canonical.com/mailman/listinfo/storm">mailing list</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
